<tool id="rxlr_eer_whisson_et_al_2007_re" name="RXLR-EER Motifs (Whisson et al. 2007, heuristic)" version="0.0.2">
    <description>Find RXLR-EER Effectors of Plant Pathogenic Oomycetes</description>
    <command interpreter="python">
      rxlr_whisson_et_al_2007_re.py $fasta_file 8 $tabular_file
      ##I want the number of threads to be a Galaxy config option...
    </command>
    <inputs>
        <param name="fasta_file" type="data" format="fasta" label="FASTA file of protein sequences" /> 
    </inputs>
    <outputs>
        <data name="tabular_file" format="tabular" label="RXLR-EER (Whisson et al. 2007 heuristic model) results" />
    </outputs>
    <requirements>
        <requirement type="binary">signalp</requirement>
    </requirements>
    <help>
    
**What it does**

Many effector proteins from Oomycete plant pathogens for manipulating the host have
been found to contain a signal peptide followed by a conserved RXLR motif (Arg, any
amino acid, Leu, Arg), and then sometimes EER (Glu, Glu, Arg). There are stiking
parallels with the malarial host-targeting signal.

This tool looks for the protein motif RXLR-EER using the heuristic regular expression
methodolgy described in Whisson et al. (2007), which was an extension of the RXLR
clasffier described in Bhattacharjee et al. (2006).

It requires a protein sequence FASTA file as input, and produces a simple tabular
file as output with one line per protein, and two columns giving the sequence ID
and whether or not it had an RXLR-EER motif (Y or N).

Declaring a protein to have an RXLR-EER motif requires a SignalP 3.0 Hidden Markov
Model (HMM) score of at least 0.9, with the Neural Network predicted cleavage site
giving a signal peptide length between 10 and 40 amino acids, with the RXLR-EER
regular expression after this and starting within 100 amino acids of the signal
peptide clevage site.

The RXLR-EER motif is defined with the regular expression R.LR.{,40}[ED][ED][KR]
which means RXLR (Arg, any amino acid, Leu, Arg), then a stretch of up to forty
amino acids before Glu/Asp, Glu/Asp, Lys/Arg. The EER part of the name is perhaps
misleading as it also allows for DDR, EEK, and so on.

Note that Whisson et al. (2007) also describes a second RXLR-EER classifier using
a Hidden Markov Model (HMM). See also Win et al. (2007) for related classifier.

**References**

Stephen C. Whisson, Petra C. Boevink, Lucy Moleleki, Anna O. Avrova, Juan G. Morales, Eleanor M. Gilroy, Miles R. Armstrong, Severine Grouffaud, Pieter van West, Sean Chapman, Ingo Hein, Ian K. Toth, Leighton Pritchard & Paul R. J. Birch
A translocation signal for delivery of oomycete effector proteins into host plant cells.
Nature 450:115-118, 2007.

Joe Win, William Morgan, Jorunn Bos, Ksenia V. Krasileva, Liliana M. Cano, Angela Chaparro-Garcia, Randa Ammar, Brian J. Staskawicz and Sophien Kamoun.
Adaptive evolution has targeted the C-terminal domain of the RXLR effectors of plant pathogenic oomycetes.
The Plant Cell 19:2349-2369, 2007.

Souvik Bhattacharjee, N. Luisa Hiller, Konstantinos Liolios, Joe Win, Thirumala-Devi Kanneganti, Carolyn Young, Sophien Kamoun and Kasturi Haldar.
The malarial host-targeting signal is conserved in the Irish potato famine pathogen.
PLoS Pathogens, 2(5):e50, 2006.

Trudy A. Torto, Shuang Li, Allison Styer, Edgar Huitema, Antonino Testa, Neil A.R. Gow, Pieter van West and Sophien Kamoun.
EST mining and functional expression assays identify extracellular effector proteins from the plant pathogen phytophthora.
Genome Research, 13:1675-1685, 2003.

Nielsen, Engelbrecht, Brunak and von Heijne.
Identification of prokaryotic and eukaryotic signal peptides and prediction of their cleavage sites.
Protein Engineering, 10:1-6, 1997.

    </help>
</tool>
