<tool id="rxlr_win_et_al_2007" name="RXLR Motifs (Win et al. 2007)" version="0.0.1">
    <description>Find RXLR Effectors of Plant Pathogenic Oomycetes</description>
    <command interpreter="python">rxlr_win_et_al_2007.py $fasta_file $signalp_file $tabular_file</command>
    <inputs>
        <param name="fasta_file" type="data" format="fasta" label="FASTA file of protein sequences" /> 
        <param name="signalp_file" type="data" format="tabular" label="Tabular file of SignalP 3.0 predictions" />
    </inputs>
    <outputs>
        <data name="tabular_file" format="tabular" label="RXLR (Win et al. 2007) results" />
    </outputs>
    <tests>
        <test>
            <param name="fasta_file" value="rxlr_win_et_al_2007.fasta" ftype="fasta" />
            <param name="signalp_file" value="rxlr_win_et_al_2007_sp3.tabular" ftype="tabular" />
            <output name="tabular_file" file="rxlr_win_et_al_2007.tabular" ftype="tabular" />
        </test>
    </tests>
    <help>
    
**What it does**

Looks for the protein motif RXLR using the methodolgy described in Win et al. (2007).

Win et al. (2007) used SignalP v2.0, which is no longer available.
The current release is SignalP v3.0 (Mar 5, 2007), and we provide a
Galaxy wrapper for this. As part of this change, we have opted to use the
Neural Network Ymax position for the predicted cleavage site, as this is
expected to be more accurate. Also note that the HMM score values have
changed from v2.0 to v3.0. 

You must first call the SignalP v3.0 tool for prediction of signal peptides on
your FASTA file of proteins, and give this output and the FASTA file as inputs.

SignalP uses both a Neural Network (NN) and Hidden Markov Model (HMM) to produce two sets of scores.
This tools requires both a positive result from the HMM (using a threshold of 0.9),
and the NN predicted cleveage site to be between amino acids 10 and 30.
Additionally the motif RXLR must be found starting between amino acids 30 and 60,
and after the NN predicted signal peptide clevage site.


**References**

Joe Win, William Morgan, Jorunn Bos, Ksenia V. Krasileva, Liliana M. Cano, Angela Chaparro-Garcia, Randa Ammar, Brian J. Staskawicz and Sophien Kamoun.
Adaptive Evolution Has Targeted the C-Terminal Domain of the RXLR Effectors of Plant Pathogenic Oomycetes
The Plant Cell 19:2349-2369, 2007.

    </help>
</tool>
