<tool id="rxlr_win_et_al_2007" name="RXLR Motifs (Win et al. 2007)" version="0.0.2">
    <description>Find RXLR Effectors of Plant Pathogenic Oomycetes</description>
    <command interpreter="python">
      rxlr_win_et_al_2007.py $fasta_file 8 $tabular_file
      ##I want the number of threads to be a Galaxy config option...
    </command>
    <inputs>
        <param name="fasta_file" type="data" format="fasta" label="FASTA file of protein sequences" /> 
    </inputs>
    <outputs>
        <data name="tabular_file" format="tabular" label="RXLR (Win et al. 2007) results" />
    </outputs>
    <requirements>
        <requirement type="binary">signalp</requirement>
    </requirements>
    <tests>
        <test>
            <param name="fasta_file" value="rxlr_win_et_al_2007.fasta" ftype="fasta" />
            <output name="tabular_file" file="rxlr_win_et_al_2007.tabular" ftype="tabular" />
        </test>
    </tests>
    <help>
    
**What it does**

Many effector proteins from Oomycete plant pathogens for manipulating the host have
been found to contain a signal peptide followed by a conserved RXLR motif (Arg, any
amino acid, Leu, Arg), and then sometimes EER (Glu, Glu, Arg). There are stiking
parallels with the malarial host-targeting signal.

This tool looks or the protein motif RXLR using the methodolgy described in Win et al.
(2007). It requires a protein sequence FASTA file as input, and produces a simple
tabular file as output with one line per protein, and two columns giving the sequence
ID and whether or not it had an RXLR motif (Y or N).

Declaring a protein to have an RXLR motif requires a SignalP Hidden Markov Model (HMM)
score of at least 0.9, with the Neural Network predicted cleavage site between amino
acids 10 and 40, with an RXLR pattern after this and starting between amino acids 30
and 60.

Note that Win et al. (2007) used SignalP v2.0, which is no longer available. The
current release is SignalP v3.0 (Mar 5, 2007), so this is used instead (with the
Eukaryote model and sequences truncated at 70 amin acids).

See also Whisson et. al (2007) for two related RXLR classifiers.


**References**

Joe Win, William Morgan, Jorunn Bos, Ksenia V. Krasileva, Liliana M. Cano, Angela Chaparro-Garcia, Randa Ammar, Brian J. Staskawicz and Sophien Kamoun.
Adaptive evolution has targeted the C-terminal domain of the RXLR effectors of plant pathogenic oomycetes.
The Plant Cell 19:2349-2369, 2007.

Stephen C. Whisson, Petra C. Boevink, Lucy Moleleki, Anna O. Avrova, Juan G. Morales, Eleanor M. Gilroy, Miles R. Armstrong, Severine Grouffaud, Pieter van West, Sean Chapman, Ingo Hein, Ian K. Toth, Leighton Pritchard and Paul R. J. Birch.
A translocation signal for delivery of oomycete effector proteins into host plant cells.
Nature 450:115-118, 2007.

Souvik Bhattacharjee, N. Luisa Hiller, Konstantinos Liolios, Joe Win, Thirumala-Devi Kanneganti, Carolyn Young, Sophien Kamoun and Kasturi Haldar.
The malarial host-targeting signal is conserved in the Irish potato famine pathogen.
PLoS Pathogens, 2(5):e50, 2006.

Trudy A. Torto, Shuang Li, Allison Styer, Edgar Huitema, Antonino Testa, Neil A.R. Gow, Pieter van West and Sophien Kamoun.
EST mining and functional expression assays identify extracellular effector proteins from the plant pathogen phytophthora.
Genome Research, 13:1675-1685, 2003.

Nielsen, Engelbrecht, Brunak and von Heijne.
Identification of prokaryotic and eukaryotic signal peptides and prediction of their cleavage sites.
Protein Engineering, 10:1-6, 1997.

    </help>
</tool>
